Some time ago AI painting kept appearing in my dynamic
Also repeatedly on the bilibili popular
Some think AI will help humans become more efficient
Some people think AI is plagiarism
Some people think AI will replace all walks of life
How AI really works
To explain this problem
I Wrote and open-sourced a simple neural network example of about 100 lines of code
without using a third-party framework
Let's take a look, together, at the inner workings of AI
I'll start by explaining the principles of neural networks in as zero-basic and no-barrier a way as possible
and then form a general impression of the principle of ai painting
First I need to reintroduce the mathematical functions
Maybe it's a little bit long and uninteresting
Viewers can speed up or skip
Using the video subsection title to jump would be better
y=x+1 is a very simple function
The shape is a line with a slope of 1
where x is the input, y is the output
Given any value of x
y will be the value added one
The function is also often written as f(x)=x+1
The parameters are in parentheses
f can refer to the effect on the input parameters
Bringing in x gives an output result
We may often encounter problems like this in school
A water tank is draining
The total amount of water is 100 liters
The rate of water discharge is 4 liters per second
Ask how much water is left after x seconds
So we list y = 100 - 4*x (0<=x<=25),
where x is the time consumed
and y is a "predicted" output for the remaining water
We can give real meaning to the input and output parameters of the function
thus solving realistic problems
A complex problem may have many parameters
We can write this as f(x1,x2,x3) = x1 + 3*x2 + 4*x3^2
Whether it's text, image, audio
These can be converted to data storage
All data can be used as arguments to the function
Get an output
For example, we want to make a simple numeric discriminant function
Pass in a three-by-three matrix
You can also think of it as an image
Assuming that its shape must be a valid number
We are asked to determine if the shape is the number 1
Because there are only nine squares
There are only 0,1,4,7 numbers that can be accommodated
We note that with the matrix
0,4 is written in only one way
7 is written in 7 ways, while 1 is written in 9 ways
We can of course determine each of these ways of writing
Only 1 needs to be checked for these nine cases
But there is a pattern here
For example
The shape of a 1 always takes up only two or three pixels
For this condition
We can filter out many other numbers
There are only four ways to write 7 left to compete with us
And the way 7 is written, there must be a middle column involved
And when 1 takes up three pixels
There is only one way to write that takes up the middle column
and is full
We can start by counting the total number of occupied pixels, y1=x1+x2+x3.... .x9
Here a coefficient matrix is hidden
We can construct another matrix
Detecting the occupation of the middle column
Written as a function is y2=x2+x5+x8
Combining these two conditions
That is, y1(total) = 2
or when y1=3 and y2(middle column)=3 or 0
represents the shape of the number 1
For this description
We can still list a function
If z=0, then that means the condition is met
The shape is the number 1
The 3D shape of z looks like this
You can see that this function is in scope
There are some intersections with the z=0 plane
i.e. the conditions just mentioned for y1,y2
where the line of the intersection of the two points of y1=2
All met with our conditions
i.e. y1=2, or y1=3 and y2=3 or 0
We can also bring y1,y2 into
We end up with a complex relationship between z and x1,x2,... .x9
This is an example of a realistic problem expressed as a function
Used to make a category determination on an image
As we said before, whether it's text, image
Audio
These can be converted to data storage
All of these can be used as function parameters
It is also possible to output according to our target
Analyze a set of laws
A relational equation
For this previous problem we know the result
Of course we can write it
Draw it directly, but in reality the problem is very complicated
We can hardly calculate the result manually
So a relatively general neural network model structure needs to be designed
This unknown result is obtained by training and adjusting the parameters
We can draw the two functions y1,y2 as a mesh
Two layers are formed
The first layer is the input, which is a three-by-three image matrix
The second layer is the processing
In a neural network it is called the hidden layer
In fact, hidden layers can also have a multi-layer recursive structure
to better fit more complex cases
It's not just one column like this
But our current problem uses only one column
(A single hidden layer can theoretically fit any function, but multiple layers perform better)
Here one by one cells
is the neuron in the neural network
Connections between neurons
is the coefficient matrix mentioned earlier
Here it is called the weights
The missing third layer here, is the output
We want to aggregate the results of the hidden layer to the output layer
The final output is the target we want the neural network to predict
Here, it's the z function that was mentioned earlier
Of course, the way we've drawn it so far
You will find
This "neural network" can only express like y=ax1+bx2+cx3 in the form
With one parameter, it is a straight line in two dimensions
With two parameters, it is a plane in three-dimensional space
In short, it is linear, it is "straight"
And the expression for z that we were going to get earlier
The drawing is a surface in 3D space
We can't express the surface through this network now
But we can switch our thinking
Breaking down our goal into "straight" pieces
and then combine them into the curves, surfaces we need
or other non-"straight" targets in higher dimensions
To achieve this
We need to use the activation function
Examples of common activation functions
sigmoid, the mathematical expression looks like this
The shape is like this
Activation functions like sigmoid make an otherwise linear function nonlinear
Eventually we can do this for various inputs
By simply adding and multiplying the coefficients that worked in the previous neural network
Combining segments, fitting arbitrary continuous curves
Expresses an arbitrary function
As long as your input and output targets
There exists the possibility of logical functional expression
so it can be written in functional form
We then achieve a mathematical expression for the specific problem
So far
We know that the actual problem can be transformed into a fixed form of mathematical equations
This neural network structure can be used to infer
This process is called forward propagation
However, in our previous numerical discrimination problem
Each formula is calculated manually
If the individual constants in the previous calculation equation
that is, the connection parameters (weights) between the neurons in the neural network,
We can get the computer to compute
so that we can have an artificial intelligence that can automatically reason about a particular problem
We can start by having the individual weights randomly generated
and then perform a simple test
Look at the incoming input data
Whether the output is what we want
This result is called a prediction,
The abbreviation is pred
If it's not what we want
We can see how much it differs from the result we want
The result we want is the true result
Write true, or target,
Here you can use, for example, the mean squared error (mse) to measure the difference with the target
where this symbol is read as sigma, which means summation
Add from 1 to n
Because we'll have a bunch of inputs and outputs
To measure the overall difference
This calculation is also well understood
To measure the difference we naturally think of subtraction
And there is no positive or negative difference
So we eliminate the negative sign by squaring
Then we sum and average to get the error
Use the square instead of the absolute value
Mainly for ease of derivation
And if the error is large (greater than 1) the square can also amplify the difference
Increase the adjustment. What is about the derivative?
Why Derivative?
And how the weights are adjusted will be explained later
In summary, this function for measuring differences
We call it the loss function,
indicates the current effect compared to the target
How much risk, how much loss
We want its value to be as small as possible
means as close to the target as possible
e.g., yes/no
can be expressed as 1,0, if the AI calculates the result as 0.9
Although not exactly what we were aiming for
But when the result is only two possible
0.9 is close to "yes"
The loss function results will be small
meaning that we are close to the target
So, next, what we're going to do
is to adjust the previously randomly generated weights
and calculating the loss function, to keep reducing the loss
aimless randomness obviously doesn't work
The number of participants for many real-world problems is very large
We need a reliable method
Starting through partial derivatives is a common method
What is a partial derivative?
First, a line in the two-dimensional plane
We know that there is a slope to describe the degree of tilt
If it is a curve
then the slope of the curve is different at different positions
We do this by taking the derivative at a particular position
to calculate the slope
The derivative is the slope at a specific position
There are a series of mathematical methods/formulas for finding the derivative
But not the point here
And if the number of parameters increases
For example to the three-dimensional space
A point on the surface has many tangents
There are many different cases of "slope",
We fix a surface, forming a plane curve
Treating all the other variables as constants
Then derive the only parameter at this point
is the partial derivative
With partial derivative/slope
What can be done about it?
In a neural network
We substitute the individual equations layer by layer
We can get a prediction and input
and the relationship equation for the weights
The prediction results are substituted into the loss function
Again, we can get the loss function with their relationship equation
We can abbreviate the loss function versus the weights as L(w1,w2,...) ,
w is the abbreviation for weightweight
The actual meaning of slope is the speed of change
If we find the partial derivative of each weight variable for the loss function
then we can measure
The effect of the individual weights on the rate of change of the loss function
If a weight variable poses a drastic effect on the loss function
The value of the bias is large
We then know that fluctuations in this weight can easily cause fluctuations in the predicted results
For example, an image
The color of just one pixel changes due to weight fluctuations
This causes the neural network to predict a dog as a cat (with fluctuating results),
This is clearly not reasonable
This weighting variable is largely responsible for the failure of the neural network's predictions
In other words
We need to adjust the weights, reduce its interference
The way to adjust it, you can just do a simple subtraction
For example, if the weight is 1, the derivative is 10
Direct 1-0.01*10 to get 0.9
By looking at the image we can find
The value of the loss function goes in the lower direction
where 0.01 is the factor by which we fine-tune the weights
Called learning rate
Avoid large direct curve adjustments
Causes large fluctuations in results
In the other case, the derivative is negative
For example -10, again the rate of change is high, -1-0.01*(-10) = -0.9
The weights have increased
The loss function also goes in the lower direction
Eventually, only a trough is reached
At this point the rate of change is flat
The weights are no longer adjusted
The loss function also drops to a low point
Now
We get the specific way to adjust the weights
This method is called stochastic gradient descent
where the gradient is related to the partial derivative
also has geometric significance
But again, not the point here
Here it's just a name
This method works under
The result of the final loss function will tend to be stable
The previously predicted process, called forward propagation
And after the prediction is obtained, the bias is calculated
and adjusting the weights in turn is called back propagation
With two loops like this
we can keep feeding our network with all kinds of pre-prepared data
Let him reason, compare the differences with the expected results
00:10:50,733 and then improve his own network weights
This whole process, which is the training of the neural network
And finally
We get a more and more definite weight
Of course this weight is not necessarily the optimal solution in the end
For example
There is a loss function associated with two input parameters
Their weights are w1,w2
We can plot this as a 3D graph
It looks like this one small hill
The lowest point, i.e. the one with the least loss
which is the value we need for the two weights w1,w2
But as we did earlier by calculating the bias
Random gradient descent
The method of letting the loss function converge, meaning
The weights we finally find
Probably the bottom of the hill we expected
It could also be the top of a gentle slope
or the bottom of the slope which is not the closest to 0
These are also places where the rate of change is flat
Weights are difficult to adjust
This means that we find the local optimal solution
How to find the theoretical optimal solution as far as possible
is a common problem in the field of artificial intelligence
For example, introducing the impulse
Accelerate or decelerate the change according to the previous change
Let's fit in the process of
No more staying at the local optimum
Eventually increasing the probability of reaching the theoretical optimum
In a nutshell, activation function, loss function
Backpropagation optimization (e.g., gradient descent to adjust weights as mentioned earlier), etc.
There are various methods
These are the main points of research in deep learning theory
All of the above knowledge
is enough to write a complete neural network
Next
I'll explain a simple neural network that I wrote using this knowledge
Its open source link on github is this
You can also find it in the profile or the top section of the comments section
Training and Inference section
In the file nn.py
nn is short for neural network
The core, which is from here
Here, there are about 100 lines of code
First of all, the initialization, we need to provide the input
For example, the number of pixels in an image
Then the number of neurons in the hidden layer
Then the activation function
The default is to use the sigmoid just described
Note that each neuron can use a separate activation function
Here I was lazy and used all the same
Then, with the initialization parameters
We then determine the structure of the neural network
Here
Random initialization of individual weights and offsets
The offset is an additional value that is added after multiplying the weight coefficients and the input
but is not required
is to be able to translate the image of our function
to make it more flexible
followed by forward propagation
hidden_layers is the output of each neuron
It results in, for each of the previous weights, a concatenated accumulation
Then using the activation function
Note that here I only used a single hidden layer
instead of multiple layers
So the hidden layers have been counted
Final
We sum up the hidden layers equally cumulatively to the output
An inferred result is obtained
The latter function is the training and backpropagation part
The first big loop, which is the training round
We have to keep fine-tuning the weights during the training rounds
Second cycle
It's the data from each training round
to make inferences and compare the differences with the expected results
Where, the variable data
is the data we use for training
and the variable next to it is our expected inference target
Here the d in d_L_d_pred
refers to the differential (it doesn't matter if you don't know the differential),
L is an abbreviation for loss, that is, the loss function
pred is an abbreviation for prediction
i.e. prediction/extrapolation
d_L_d_pred is also the derivative/rate of change of the loss function with respect to the predicted outcome
The loss function is not calculated directly here
Here you can see the loss function mse_loss
is subtracted for a series of objectives and predicted outcomes
Squaring, then taking the mean
which is the mean squared error that we have mentioned before
And as we mentioned before
We have to calculate the loss function
Take the derivative
Then adjust the weights to stabilize the loss
So
The loss function is a part of the final functional equation
So in this program
we directly calculate the derivative of the mean squared error
Here the direct use of high school knowledge of derivatives gives the result as
-2 * (output_target - output_prediction)
The next series of variables of the form d_x_d_y
are the derivatives for each connected part of the neural network
And here are some abbreviations
For example, w refers to the weight weight, and hl for example
refers to the hidden layer
The specific formula method is not explained here
The program uses all the knowledge from high school
Finally, the adjustment of the weights
including the learn_rate here
As already mentioned
The final loss function value calculated again
Just for display to the screen
For trainers to view
That's the entire logic of the simple neural network program
Inside main.py is a concrete example of simple usage
Here we use four 3x3 matrices
The shapes are 0, 1, 4, 7
This is our example, as input
Then set their expected target
i.e. 0, 1, 4, 7
Here the target is also divided by 10
is to normalize all our data
Distributed between 0 and 1
Because our weights will be initialized to a very small range of values
The amount of adjustment of the weights is also a small fine adjustment
If we have a large input
After the activation function, the value is still large
The final prediction is huge
The derivative is still large
which in turn causes the weights to be updated significantly
Dramatic fluctuations
If the weights are randomly very large or very small negative numbers at the beginning
will face the same problem
This problem is called gradient explosion
Normalization allows our model to better fit the target
and avoid gradient explosion
Anyway, finally
We create the previously written neural network
The input is a 3x3 matrix
The hidden layer has 9 neurons
Then training, incoming data and target
After training, then prediction
The prediction is implemented by calling the forward propagation
You can see that the prediction is successful
You can also adjust the number of hidden layer neurons yourself
And look at the success rate of the prediction
Of course, there is very little data here
There is an overfitting problem
That is, this neural network will become only for this data and result
And, here the data is used for both training
and also for testing, is not appropriate
Even if all succeed
We also don't know how well it works for other data
Next, there is the advanced part
How to recognize human handwritten numbers?
If you train directly with this network
trying to get it to be able to judge 0-9 in one breath you would find
In the end the neural network always outputs a number
This is because, mindless guessing
Or just output the same number
The final success rate is 10%,
The final mean square error is converging
The loss function is stable
Meets our design objective
That is, the AI swings badly, within our rules
Get the guarantee and leave
Actually, the handwritten numbers
The situation is very complicated, for example, the numbers 1 and 7 are very similar
3 is similar to 5, 6 is similar to 9
Sometimes humans can't always tell the difference
For ai
Output 0.1 and 0.7, which is too big a difference
The difference in weight needed is huge
But in fact the two cases are similar for us
That's a tough one.
So, we need to change our thinking
For example, we can use ten neural networks
Each network only judges one number
For example, to determine if the number is 5 only
Either yes or no
We write a number by hand
Ten networks working together
Finally
See which network has the highest probability of being yes (result closest to 1),
We will consider the neural network to be judging this number
In the usps folder
train.py in this file
I trained the handwritten data of usps with this method
and used only a single neuron hidden layer
The final test accuracy is close to 90%
I made some simplifications to the weights
Only the integer part is kept
The accuracy is still 87%,
There is also a lot of research in the field of deep learning on model tailoring
My simplification is very crude in this way
After saving the weights as a json file, you can see that
There is only a tiny bit of this number here
After compressing the 10 network weights, the volume is only about 1kb
Not even a regular image
This achieves a very rough handwritten number recognition
Of course, this neural network is very simple
There is only one hidden layer
And there's a lot of deep learning field methods that are not applied
For example, fast training of multiple batch inputs
More efficient convolution operations for image processing
Pooling operation for compressed features
Softmax activation functions and cross-entropy loss functions that are more efficient for classification problems
Common neural networks are able to achieve over 99% accuracy for this kind of number detection
If you are interested, you can also do your own search based on keywords
In addition to the categories
The output can also be, for example, an x-axis or y-axis coordinate
Width, height of an object form
These combined
and it becomes the target detection
Neural networks can do a lot more than that.
However, neural networks are not a panacea
Not everything can be fitted by being as complex as possible
What neural networks can fit, just functions
The set output is not optional either
Instead, a logical level of possibility is required
I believe that everyone who is reading this
How neural networks work, the details
Neural networks are really like regular summaries based on your data and goals
You have to design the right network model
Using various techniques
Find this expected pattern as much as possible
If there are logically possible mathematical expressions for the inputs and outputs you envision, theoretically you can fit
If you can understand the brain
the workings of various cells, digitizing every cell, atom, and digitizing the entire planet, maybe we could see the future.
And finally, about AI painting
ai is summarizing the laws
There is no thought per se, ai painting does not carry out a common understanding of copying and stitching
But there may be stitches in the regular set
Similar to
What the incoming tags represent roughly
This leg looks like this
The next part of the texture should be drawn like this or like that
And this pattern
does originate from the work of painters whose AI is used as data
but obtained by AI analysis training
In addition
If you give the data and the goal is to plagiarize
then ai will do the same
So you might see ai directly along with the composition
The case where the painting style is imitated together
For the future
After the AI has trained an initial result
It is possible to make targeted adjustments based on human preferences
Set evolutionary direction
For example, how does this drawing look better to the public?
The developer can adjust the training data accordingly
Retaining pleasing data, further deepening
Maybe it will gradually develop its own style
That is, summarize the laws of popular preference
The complete body, which is the equivalent of thousands of people constantly picking at the painting and adjusting it
The result
I think it's bound to have a huge impact on the related industries
But I also believe that ai can bring more possibilities for human beings
After all, the development of technology
did lead to a better life for mankind
And the never-ending curiosity of mankind
Understanding and experimenting with the unknown
is something that AI can never replace
What humans will eventually do, only humans know.